When it comes to what you eat,
there's no shortage of advice.
TikTok is overflowing with it...
the low-carb diet, raw food,
cabbage soup, cucumber bagel diet.
And on and on.
If you're confused, it's no wonder.
So here's five simple tips
you can trust for healthy eating.
OK, this one's
a bit of a game-changer.
If you eat a treat -
say a slice of chocolate cake -
it's much better to eat it
after a meal than on its own.
Why?
It's all about keeping
glucose spikes under control.
Whenever you eat carbs,
or sweet things,
the level of glucose
in your blood rises.
If it rises very quickly,
and sharply,
it will be followed by a crash.
And that crash makes you feel tired,
irritable,
and hungry again.
But there are ways to keep
these spikes under control.
Exercising after you eat is one.
Eating foods higher in fibre -
like vegetables or porridge oats -
is another.
But the order you eat your food
matters too.
If you're having something
carb-heavy -
like white rice or pasta -
eating fat, protein,
or vegetables before
flattens that glucose curve.
A little bit of fish, meat,
broccoli, an egg...
anything like that would do.
That's because having something
in your stomach first
slows down how quickly
the carbohydrates
reach the small intestine
for digestion.
And it's the same for that slice
of chocolate cake.
Why?
Well, for a start,
it's notoriously hard to do.
Most people underestimate
their calorie intake by about 25%.
But also because not all calories
behave in the same way,
once inside your body.
Foods in their natural state -
like nuts, fruit, vegetables,
and fish, or anything
that's not been processed -
require more energy from the body
to digest them.
This is called
the thermic effect of food.
And it means that
things like nuts,
which are high in calories,
can still be a healthy option,
as the body uses so much energy
digesting them.
In recent years, scientists
have begun to understand
the importance of
what's known as the
gut microbiome.
The gut microbiome is
everything in the digestive tract.
It's a huge ecosystem
that contains trillions of bacteria,
fungi, viruses and cells.
And it can weigh as much as 2 kilos.
Research suggests the make-up
of your gut microbiome
could have really profound effects
on your physical health,
and potentially
on your mental health too.
For a healthy microbiome,
and a healthy you,
you should aim to eat a wide range
of different foods.
Seeds, fruit, vegetables,
the yoghurt drink kefir
and other fermented foods
are particularly gut-friendly.
In the UK, 57% of calories we eat
come from ultra-processed foods.
And this figure is even higher
for children.
Ultra-processed foods include,
as you might expect,
things like pizza, ready meals,
biscuits.
But also some quite surprising
things,
which tend to be thought of
as healthy -
like most supermarket breads,
many breakfast cereals,
and many milk and meat substitutes.
UPF are not labelled.
But a good a rule of thumb
is to look for ingredients
you don't recognise.
Things you'd never have
in your own kitchen.
Like emulsifiers, sweeteners,
colourings and preservatives.
Another approach
that's on the rise at the moment
is that of personalised nutrition.
And in 2014, two scientists,
Eran Segal and Eran Elinav,
found some really surprising
results from an experiment.
The blood glucose levels
in their sample group varied widely
after people ate the same food.
The explanation?
Well, it could be
back to the make-up
of our unique gut microbiomes.
The dream of personalised nutrition
is that people would be able
to tailor their food choices
to the specific needs
of their bodies.
But nutritionists are keen to
point out that some key messages
still apply across the board.
So, for a healthy diet,
aim for foods which are close
to their natural state...
An orange instead of orange juice.
Brown rice instead of white rice.
Dark chocolate
instead of milk chocolate.
Aim for a wide variety of foods.
Try not to eat too many ingredients
you don't recognise.
And remember, you are what you eat.
But when you eat matters too.